Guide to the Rhoda Richardson Papers 1908
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Rhoda Richardson Papers
1908
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 466
Richardson, Rhoda, 1892-1978
0.2 linear feet
Rhoda Richardson was a resident of Lothrop and Missoula, Montana. The collection consists of her memories and photographs of the 1908 flood in western Montana.
Biographical Note
Rhoda Richardson was born on May 12, 1892, in Butte, Montana, to Charles and Annie Brown Richardson. Her father was in charge of W.A. Clark's logging enterprises in Butte, Montana. When Richardson was twelve years old, the family moved to Lothrop, Montana. She attended high school in Missoula. Around 1921, she permanently moved to Missoula, Montana. For several years she worked as an office clerk at Northern Pacific Railroad. She was a member of the Episcopal Church of the Holy Spirit, the Brotherhood of Railway Clerks, and Chapter AT, PEO. Richardson died on December 6, 1978, in Missoula, Montana.
The collection contains materials related to the 1908 flood in western Montana, including reminiscence by Rhoda Richardson and photographs.
The collection is divided into two series:
Series I: Reminiscence, 0.1 linear feet, undated
Series II: Photographs, 24 photographs, 1908
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
The collection was originally donated to the Missoula City-County Library by Rhoda Richardson.
Gift of Rhoda Richardson through the Missoula City-County Library, date unknown.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Photographs--Montana--Missoula County; Reminiscences--Montana--Missoula County
Canadian Americans--Montana--Missoula--Biography; Floods--Clark Fork (Mont. and Idaho); Floods--Clark Fork (Mont. and Idaho)--Photographs; Logging--Montana--Ninemile Creek (Missoula County)--Photographs
Lothrop (Mont.)
Beckwith, Charles E., 1836-1928--Biography; Hammond, Andrew B. (Andrew Benoni), 1848-1934--Biography
Montana; Logging; Women
- Reminiscence, undated; Series I; 0.1 linear feet
  The series contains a carbon copy of a reminiscence Rhoda Richardson wrote about her early life in Lothrop, Montana, and the flood of 1908, in particular. The series also contains short biographies Richardson wrote about Andrew B. Hammond and Charles E. Beckwith.
  - Western Montana Flood, undated (Box-folder 1/1)
- Photographs, 1908; Series II; 24 photographs
  The series contains photographs of the 1908 flood of the Clark Fork River (then known as the Missoula River) in western Montana. The photographs include the Higgins Avenue Bridge in Missoula and the lumberyard at Lothrop, Montana. The series also contains photographs of logging at Ninemile Creek.
  The series is arranged in subject order.
  - Higgins Avenue Bridge, Missoula, Montana, ca. 1908; 466(II)1 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Higgins Avenue Bridge, Missoula, Montana, ca. 1908; 466(II)2 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Missoula River at Lothrop, Montana, during flood, 1908; 466(II)3 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Lothrop Bridge, Lothrop, Montana, ca. 1908; 466(II)4 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - "All that was left of the Lothrop Bridge," N.P.R.R. tracks in foreground, Lothrop, Montana, June 1908; 466(II)5 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - buildings at Lothrop, Montana, during flood, 1908; 466(II)6 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - lumber yard and buildings underwater at Lothrop, Montana, 1908; 466(II)7 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - buildings underwater at Lothrop, Montana, 1908; 466(II)8 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - mill and bunk houses, house and office at Lothrop, Montana, flood, 1908; 466(II)9 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Lothrop Mill during flood, Lothrop, Montana, 1908; 466(II)10 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - lumberyard and buildings during flood, Lothrop, Montana, 1908; 466(II)11 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - lumberyard in winter at Lothrop, Montana, ca.1908; 466(II)12 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - lumberyard at Lothrop, Montana, ca. 1908; 466(II)13 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - lumberyard at Lothrop, Montana, ca. 1908; 466(II)14 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - lumberyard at Lothrop, Montana, during flood, 1908; 466(II)15 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - lumberyard at Lothrop, Montana, during flood, 1908; 466(II)16 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - logs at landing on Ninemile Creek, ca. 1908; 466(II)17 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - logs at landing on Ninemile Creek, ca. 1908; 466(II)18 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - "Old time logging methods", 1908; 466(II)19 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Logging at Lothrop, Montana, 1908; 466(II)20 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Horse team (view from behind) hauling logs at Lothrop, Montana, ca. 1908; 466(II)21 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Ranch vegetable garden at Lothrop (?), Montana, ca. 1908; 466(II)22 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - House at Lothrop (?), Montana, ca. 1908; 466(II)23 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - "Nello" the dog at Lothrop (?), Montana, house, ca. 1908; 466(II)24 (Box-folder 1/24)